Guide to the James Morgan Hart papers, 1856-1916.
Hart, James Morgan papers, 1856-1916
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
James Morgan Hart papers, 1856-1916.
14-18-65
J. M. (James Morgan) Hart, 1839-1916.
6.5 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, photograph albums, and a scrapbook.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes letters from scholars relating to the study of languages and literature, particularly Old English, Celtic, and German, and to scholarly language journals and associations; from educators relating to university patterns and policies at Cornell; from editors concerning Hart's publications; from Mrs. Bayard Taylor regarding her husband's papers; autographed letters from Louisa May Alcott, Richard Henry Dana, Jr., Hamilton Fish, Henry James, Henry W. Longfellow, Lord Russell, and others addressed to Hart's father, John Seeley Hart; notes on German and English literature; photograph albums of family and friends; scrapbook of Hart's letters to newspapers; typescript copies of letters of Will Doherty relating to entomological collecting trips in Asia, Africa, and Europe; letters from Hart to his parents commenting on his student days at Princeton and Göttingen, his life as a law clerk in New York City, and his experiences as an instructor at Cornell and in subsequent teaching posts; and letters from T.F. Crane commenting on affairs at Cornell University.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes letters from scholars relating to the study of languages and literature, particularly Old English, Celtic, and German, and to scholarly language journals and associations: F.D. Allen, C.A. Buchheim, Albert S. Cook, Lane Cooper, Hiram Corson, T.F. Crane, E.A. Eggers, A.B. Faust, Charles E. Hart, B.L. Gildersleeve, Gustaf E. Karsten, E.S. Sheldon, Albert H. Smyth, F.H. Stoddard, E.B. Titchener, Frederick Tupper, Albert S. Wheeler; from educators relating to university patterns and policies at Cornell: Charles K. Adams, F.A.P. Barnard, Charles W. Eliot; from editors concerning Hart's publications; from Mrs. Bayard Taylor regarding her husband's papers; autographed letters from Louisa May Alcott, Richard Henry Dana, Jr., Hamilton Fish, Henry James, Henry W. Longfellow, Lord Russell, and others addressed to Hart's father, John Seeley Hart; notes on German and English literature; photograph albums of family and friends; scrapbook of Hart's letters to newspapers; typescript copies of letters of Will Doherty relating to entomological collecting trips in Asia, Africa, and Europe; letters from Hart to his parents (1856-1887) commenting on his student days at Princeton and Göttingen, his life as a law clerk in New York City, and his experiences as an instructor at Cornell (1868-1872) and in subsequent teaching posts; and letters from T.F. Crane (1872-1890) commenting on affairs at Cornell University.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Hart, J. M. (James Morgan), 1839-1916.; Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Alcott, Louisa May, 1832-1888.; Allen, F. D. (Frederick De Forest), 1844-1897.; Barnard, Frederick A. P. (Frederick Augustus Porter), 1809-1889.; Buchheim, C. A. (Carl Adolf), 1828-1900.; Cook, Albert S. (Albert Stanburrough), 1853-1927.; Cooper, Lane, 1875-1959.; Corson, Hiram, 1828-1911.; Crane, T. F.; Dana, Richard Henry, 1815-1882.; Doherty, Will.; Eggers, E. A.; Eliot, Charles W.; Faust, Albert Bernhardt, 1870-1951.; Fish, Hamilton, 1888-; Gildersleeve, Basil L.(Basil Lanneau), 1831-1924.; Hart, Charles E. (Charles Edward), 1838-1916.; Hart, John S. (John Seeley), 1810-1877.; James, Henry, 1843-1916.; Karsten, Gustaf E., 1859-1908.; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882.; Russell, John Russell, 1792-1878.; Sheldon, E. S. (Edward Stevens), 1851-1925.; Smyth, Albert Henry, 1863-1907.; Stoddard, F. H.; Taylor, Bayard, Mrs.; Titchener, Edward Bradford, 1867-1927.; Tupper, Frederick, 1871-1950.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.; Wheeler, Albert S.; Cornell University--Faculty.
Subjects:
Languages--Study and teaching.; Literature--Study and teaching.; English literature.; German literature.; Philology.; Entomology.; Philologists.; College teachers.
Places:
Asia.; Africa.; Europe.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Notebooks, journals, account books, photograph albums (Box 1-5)
- A-Co Correspondence (Box 6)
- Cu-Gar Correspondence (Box 7)
- Gas-Hart Correspondence
  - Gas-Gum (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
  - Haertel-Hart, C.E. (C.E. Hart, a cousin of J.M.H.? Includes a letter from C[harles] E. Hart to J.M.H., introducing Lane Cooper, New Brunswick, N.J., Apr. 21, 1902) (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence with wife and daughter (?), 1893-1911 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - J.M. Hart to parents (John S. Hart), May 12, 1857-Aug. 14, 1887 (Box 8, Folder 7-14)
  - John S. Hart to J.M. Hart, Aug. 18, 1857-Sept. 17, 1876 (Box 8, Folder 15-21)
- Hartt-P Correspondence (Box 9)
- R-Z Correspondence (Box 10)
- JMH's judicial thesis and volumes of notes in German while studying in Germany, 1863-1864 (Box 11)
- Alpha Delta Phi material, printed items and rolled resolution from the University of Cincinnati faculty expressing regret at JMH's resignation to accept a chair at Cornell University, May 1890 (Box 11)
- Notebooks (Box 12-13)
- Essays and articles1868-1876 (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets1874-1897 (Box 14)
- Hart - Review of Zahn's Cyprian von Autochien December 1882 (Box 14)
- Hart - Articles in Modern Language Notes 1886-1887 (Box 14)
- Hart - Articles in Modern Language Notes 1887 (Box 14)
- The AcademyApril 1892 (Box 14)
- Review of Johnson's English Words 1892 (Box 14)
- Reviews of J. M. Hart, Rhetoric; Baldwin-Lewis 1895-1986 (Box 14)
- Regents Examination Bulletin June, 1897 (Box 14)
- Grimald - Christus Redivivus (Box 14)
- Miscellaneous pamphlets 1898 (Box 14)
- Five loose volumes: Typescripts of W. Doherty's correspondence, 1880-1890 (Box 15)
- One loose scrapbook: Clippings of JMH's letters to newspapers (Box 15)
- Oversize items, diplomas (Map-case S6)